Sanya Bathla Taneja

Email: <u>sbt12@pitt.edu</u>

Website: sanyabt.github.io

LinkedIn | GitHub | Semantic Scholar

EXPERIENCE

National Library of Medicine, National Institutes of Health (NIH) Research Intern | May – July 2023

 Developed entity linking methods for diseases in PubMed articles using natural language processing with biomedical ontologies, BERT-based models, and ChatGPT API with Langchain library.

University of Pittsburgh, Intelligent Systems Program Graduate Student Researcher | February 2020 - Present

- Led <u>knowledge graph</u> research and development with 700K nodes and 7M edges, combining literature-based discovery and biomedical ontologies for generation of mechanistic hypotheses for natural product-drug interactions and adverse events.
 Presented related work at <u>5 conferences</u>, <u>with 1 Best Poster Award</u> and <u>1 first-author</u> <u>peer-reviewed publication</u>.
- Developed <u>custom OMOP vocabulary</u> and OBO ontology representations for 300 natural products and constituents for pharmacovigilance.
- Responsible for longitudinal EHR data extraction, data analysis, and technical development of machine learning and case-control epidemiological analyses OMOP Common Data Model for Alzheimer's disease risk factors using OHDSI methods in R and Python, with <u>1 peer-reviewed publication</u> and <u>2 conference presentations</u>.

University of Pittsburgh, School of Medicine Research Assistant | September 2018 - February 2020

- Developed natural language processing and machine learning pipelines for twitter surveillance of vaping.
- Responsible for <u>RITHM</u> software framework maintenance, documentation, and upkeep of the GitHub repository for real-time Twitter data mining, with <u>3 peer</u> <u>reviewed publications</u>.

University of Pittsburgh and Malawi, Africa Research Intern | June – August 2019

 Developed Bayesian networks and machine learning models to diagnose childhood malaria in Malawi in collaboration with Global Health Informatics Institute in Malawi.

Amazon India

Software Development Engineer Intern | February - July 2018

• Developed backend APIs for the Seller and Retail website using Java, Spring MVC, Coral, JavaScript, and Handlebars.

EDUCATION

PhD Intelligent Systems | University of Pittsburgh | 2020-2024 MS Intelligent Systems | University of Pittsburgh | 2020 B.Tech. Computer Science and Engineering | Indira Gandhi Delhi Technical University | 2018

SUMMARY

PhD candidate in Intelligent Systems and computer scientist with research experience in natural language processing, machine learning, and knowledge representation and their applications in healthcare. Proficient in Python and SQL, with strong communication and writing skills.

SKILLS AND INTERESTS

Skills and Interests: Machine Learning, Natural Language Processing, OMOP Common Data Model, EHR Data Analysis, Bayesian Networks, Knowledge Graphs, Biomedical Ontologies, Scientific Writing Technologies: Python, SQL, R,

Git, C++, RDF, OWL

Libraries: NLTK, Spacy, Pandas,
Scikit-learn, Keras, Networkx,
Tensorflow

PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

- Student Editorial Board Member, Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association (JAMIA) | 2022-2023
- Peer Review (Journal of Biomedical Informatics, Bioinformatics, BMC Bioinformatics, Intelligent Systems for Molecular Biology, AMIA Informatics Summit)
- Co-organized & coordinated discussion group on Symbolic AI and Knowledge Graphs with 20 participants and 6 guest speakers | 2022
- Awarded Provost
 Fellowship | 2023